<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>EMERGENT</title>
    <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on EMERGENT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Genetics of strain-specific levels of toxin production in *Staphylococcus aureus*</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/kyle-michelles_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/kyle-michelles_paper/</guid>
      <description>(This article was written as part of Kyle&amp;rsquo;s Emory REAL program studentship with the lab)
Su, M., Lyles, J. T., Petit, R. A., III, Peterson, J., Hargita, M., Tang, H., Solis-Lemus, C., Quave, C. L., &amp;amp; Read, T. D. (2020). Genomic analysis of variability in Delta-toxin levels between Staphylococcus aureus strains. PeerJ, 8, e8717. https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.8717
Extracellular toxins play a central role in many Staphylococcus aureus infections. However, producing toxins can take resources away from other cellular functions, and may in fact limit bacterial growth and come at a negative fitness cost.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 Atlanta Science Festival :(</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/asf2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/asf2020/</guid>
      <description>In March this year we were looking forward to putting together a booth for the group’s first Atlanta Science Festival. We were going to represent the Infectious Diseases Division and we were going to put together fun educational activities for the general public. We held several serious meetings. When the year turned, and we realized how little time was left we really got serious and really started making plans. Then COVID-19 happened.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bacterial strain names and Biosample IDs</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/bacterial_strain_names/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/bacterial_strain_names/</guid>
      <description>The public databases maintained by NCBI and other members of the International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration (INSDC) are central resources for bacterial bioinformatic analysis. Two key concepts to know about working with these databases are BioProject and BioSample. These were created1 at NCBI as genome data began to gush in, at the beginning of the 2010s following the development of “second generation” sequencing technologies. The structure is mirrored between the INSDC databases, although IDs for the same data can be different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seven significant bacterial genomics papers from the 2010s</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/genomics_papers_2010s/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/genomics_papers_2010s/</guid>
      <description>If you recognize the birth of bacterial genomics as the 1995 publication of the complete genome sequence of Haemophilus influenzae Rd1 then the field reached the beginning of the 2010s in adolescence and by the end of the decade had matured into adulthood. Much of the progress was driven by the steadily increasing output and decreasing costs of the workhorse Illumina short read sequencing platform. This meant more genomes per dollar, and with higher per base coverage, relatively few errors in the assembled portions of the genome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting to grips with Nextflow</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/basic-nextflow-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/basic-nextflow-script/</guid>
      <description>What is Nextflow and why do I need it? A recent blog post identified three components of modern bioinformatics that elevate a user from an early stage code hacker to an efficient power user. These are containers, cloud computing and workflow software. The other two components will be discussed in other posts but the focus here is on workflows, which allows you to string together programs in reproducible, optimized pipelines that ultimately save time (and money if you want to scale up analysis to the cloud one day).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Bioconda on MacOS / Linux</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/conda-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/conda-intro/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to Bioconda on MacOS / Linux By Tim Read, October 2019
What? Over the past few years, conda, an open-source package manager, has seen rapid growth in the number of available programs it distributes (via Anaconda Cloud). A useful feature of conda is it allows programs to be separated into channels. Bioconda is one of these channels specializing in maintaining bioinformatic software.
Why? Installing open source software from source (ie the files containing the programs) is hard and time-consuming and often futile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomics of MRSA evolution and persistence on the human body</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/mrsa-evolution-persistence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2019 06:45:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/mrsa-evolution-persistence/</guid>
      <description>Read TD, Petit III RA, Yin Z, Montgomery T, McNulty MC, David MZ. USA300 Staphylococcus aureus persists on multiple body sites following an infection. BMC Microbiol [Internet]. 2018 Dec 5;18(1):206. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866-018-1336-z
Microbiologists know surprisingly little about the dynamics of bacterial life on the human body: how strains are acquired, how they move between body sites and how long it takes for them to die off or be replaced.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/tim-read/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/tim-read/</guid>
      <description>I studied Biology at the University of London and then completed a PhD in Genetics at the University of Leicester (my project centered around barriers to conjugation by E. coli plasmids). I did postdocs at Emory in molecular genetics of bacterial pathogeneisis before moving to become a faculy member at The Institute for Genomic Research (TIGR). Following a spell running the Genomics group of the Navy&amp;rsquo;s Biological Defense Research Research Directorate, I returned to Emory as a faculty in the School of Medicine in 2009.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 11:56:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description>Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) The Gram-positive bacterium S. aureus is one of the leading causes of hospital-acquired infection in the US. Research projects have charactized the genomic epidemiology of clinical isolates and used genome-wide association approaches to understand the genetic basis of antibiotic-resistance, toxin production and phage resistance. We have also developed the “Staphopia” database of whole genome variation in more than 40,000 publically-available sequenced strains.
Chlamydia Bacteria of the Chlamydia genus cause a wide range of infections in humans and animals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 11:56:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>EMERGENT is the research group of Timothy Read, based in the Division of Infectious Diseases, Emory University School of Medicine, and other scientists with similar interests at Emory. The Read lab focuses on population genomics of bacterial pathogens. Bacterial species consist of vast collection of individual cells, each with histories shaped by mutation and horizontal gene transfer. We are interested in the evolution of virulence, antibiotic resistance and transmissability and the trade-offs, metagenomic analysis of clinical specimens and diagnostic design, andevelopment of bioinformatic tools and databases for rapid genome analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Group</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 11:56:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/</guid>
      <description>EMERGENT Group The Read lab is based in the School of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases at Emory University in Atlanta, Georgia.
Read lab September 2019 L-R: Poulami (Fall rotation student), Jon, Tim, Michelle H (back), Michelle S., Robert, Ashley
Current Members Tim Read (PI/Advisor)      Michelle Hargita (Senior Research Associate)      Robert Petit (Senior Bioinformaticist)      Jon Moller (MMG Graduate Student)      Ashley Alexander (PBEE Graduate Student)      Michelle Su (MMG Graduate Student)      Emily Wissel (SON Graduate Student)      Vishnu Raghuram (MMG Graduate Student)       Former Members Tauqeer Alam, Daniel Cox, Jamie Davis, Matthew Ezewudo, Michael Frisch, Chad Haase, Sandeep Joseph, Karla Passalacqua, Jessica Peterson, Kranthi Vavikolanu, Milton Tan</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/_template/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/_template/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/abraham-moller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/abraham-moller/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/ashley-alexander/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/ashley-alexander/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/emily-wissel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/emily-wissel/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/michelle-hargita/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/michelle-hargita/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/michelle-su/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/michelle-su/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/robert-petit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/robert-petit/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/vishnu-raghuram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/vishnu-raghuram/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>