<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>EMERGENT</title>
    <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on EMERGENT</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2019 06:45:13 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomics of MRSA evolution and persistence on the human body</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/mrsa-evolution-persistence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2019 06:45:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/blog/posts/mrsa-evolution-persistence/</guid>
      <description>Read TD, Petit III RA, Yin Z, Montgomery T, McNulty MC, David MZ. USA300 Staphylococcus aureus persists on multiple body sites following an infection. BMC Microbiol [Internet]. 2018 Dec 5;18(1):206. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866-018-1336-z
Microbiologists know surprisingly little about the dynamics of bacterial life on the human body: how strains are acquired, how they move between body sites and how long it takes for them to die off or be replaced.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/tim-read/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/tim-read/</guid>
      <description>I studied Biology at the University of London and then completed a PhD in Genetics at the University of Leicester (my project centered around barriers to conjugation by E. coli plasmids). I did postdocs at Emory in molecular genetics of bacterial pathogeneisis before moving to become a faculy member at The Institute for Genomic Research (TIGR). Following a spell running the Genomics group of the Navy&amp;rsquo;s Biological Defense Research Research Directorate, I returned to Emory as a faculty in the School of Medicine in 2009.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 11:56:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description>Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) The Gram-positive bacterium S. aureus is one of the leading causes of hospital-acquired infection in the US. Research projects have charactized the genomic epidemiology of clinical isolates and used genome-wide association approaches to understand the genetic basis of antibiotic-resistance, toxin production and phage resistance. We have also developed the “Staphopia” database of whole genome variation in more than 40,000 publically-available sequenced strains.
Chlamydia Bacteria of the Chlamydia genus cause a wide range of infections in humans and animals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 11:56:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>EMERGENT is the research group of Timothy Read, based in the Division of Infectious Diseases, Emory University School of Medicine, and other scientists with similar interests at Emory. The Read lab focuses on population genomics of bacterial pathogens. Bacterial species consist of vast collection of individual cells, each with histories shaped by mutation and horizontal gene transfer. We are interested in the evolution of virulence, antibiotic resistance and transmissability and the trade-offs, metagenomic analysis of clinical specimens and diagnostic design, andevelopment of bioinformatic tools and databases for rapid genome analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Group</title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 11:56:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/</guid>
      <description>EMERGENT Group The Read lab is based in the School of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases at Emory University in Atlanta, Georgia.
Read lab September 2019 L-R: Poulami (Fall rotation student), Jon, Tim, Michelle H (back), Michelle S., Robert, Ashley
Current Members Tim Read (PI/Advisor)      Michelle Hargita (Senior Research Associate)      Robert Petit (Senior Bioinformaticist)      Ashley Alexander (PBEE Graduate Student)      Michelle Su (MMG Graduate Student)      Jon Moller (MMG Graduate Student)       Former Members Tauqeer Alam, Daniel Cox, Jamie Davis, Matthew Ezewudo, Michael Frisch, Chad Haase, Sandeep Joseph, Karla Passalacqua, Jessica Peterson, Kranthi Vavikolanu, Milton Tan</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/_template/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/_template/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/abraham-moller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/abraham-moller/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/ashley-alexander/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/ashley-alexander/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/michelle-hargita/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/michelle-hargita/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/michelle-su/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/michelle-su/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/robert-petit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://read-lab-confederation.github.io/group/robert-petit/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>